[music]
Andrew Feldman, CEO of Cerebrus, his
fifth startup. He went to Stanford,
played soccer there. He met his wife
over Argentinian tango. He created a
46,000
mm, 4 trillion transistors. Do you have
it with you? Okay. This is a million
dollars. If you want a quick a quick,
you know, cash infusion,
sell this on eBay. Okay.
All right. Uh, fastest in the world in
inference. Steve Jobs insisted the Mac
boot up 10 seconds faster. This is that
solution for AI claimed it could save
100 human lifetimes every year. Speed
matters at Cerebrus. These guys are
fast. Um, the chip industry is 70 years
old.
>> Hold on. Wouldn't it be great if he
introduced me at Thanksgiving to I mean
my brothers the doctors would have
nothing to say at the table. That would
be phenomenal.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Right. The chip industry is
70 years old and Cerebrus is taking the
hardest path. And uh you know like an
Indiana Jones movie. They're winning and
they're getting there. And this this
panel is partly about hardware and what
we need to know. And it's really fitting
that Raza is here. Uh, hosted the
speaker VIP reception. Who was there
last night? Okay. Who has house envy?
You can't buy it. He's not selling. Uh,
but it is beloved in the semiconductor
industry. And it's really fitting that
he could be here because he knows where
it's come from. He built the foundation
to where it is today. And as we talk
about where we're going, uh, this is a
great connection. All right. Dave is
probably the cleverest, most
resourceful, most tenacious uh
entrepreneur
I know. When he was at MIT, uh he he at
midnight would get computer time to do
uh AI stuff. He had a connection with
Minsky's lab. He's my business partner
by day. And I asked him to be part of
this because he is using AI every day to
kind of figure out how to solve some of
the trillion dollar opportunities around
um speed. And it's it's just very
fitting to to have this uh this panel.
All right. So, we have three people uh
on this stage who have built the chips,
funded the companies, and taken on some
of the biggest players in the industry.
Dave just sold a company for 100
million. He wants to plow that money
into the the chip industry. Uh AI
conversations tend to be about models.
Today, we're going to talk about going
underneath them to the machine, actually
running AI, and whether we're building
the right one. Every conversation about
AI right now is about the model. So now
we are going to talk about the thing you
know that that is the uh foundation. The
models get all the headlines. The
hardware gets all the problems. Let's
start there. Okay. Andrew, can you just
stand up and tell us what your life has
been like? You took a company public.
You're a bill fractional. No, you're a
multi-billionaire right now. Um on
paper, you know what is what is your
world right right now? And why is Jensen
calling you? A year and a half ago, I
interviewed him at his big supernova
event when he was like a guy, you know,
people knew him. He had that that
million-dollar chip he would walk
around, but he was you weren't taken as
seriously as you totally are now. What
has changed and and what's your plan?
>> I I think for you entrepreneurs out
there, you
when a little success comes your way, um
you're the same bozo as before there was
success, right? and and that's that's
the truth. Um I I think we are the same
team that that started this 10 years
ago. Um the things we like are the same.
Um I I think we we went public in in May
and one of the large in the largest semi
in history. Um all the problems that we
had before the IPO are there after the
IPO.
Right? The IPO solves nothing. I think
it gives you a little more money, but it
can't help you solve a technical
problem. It can't figure out a
solution to to droop across a a printed
circuit board. It it can't design chips.
And so, uh, we embarked 10 years ago on
on a big journey. And, uh, we we don't
do this for money. We we we don't do
this for to to sit and talk before you.
We we do this because we we really don't
know how to not build stuff,
right? that that even my my co-founders
and and the the thousand plus of us now
at Cerebrus
when we get a little bit of of free time
we go home and we build stuff at home.
Sometimes it's with software, sometimes
it's cabinet, sometimes it's metal work,
sometimes it's but that's who we are and
th those are the things we love doing.
And so when in 2015 we we saw the rise
of uh of AI on the horizon, we we
thought there was something uh we could
do and as as a te knows that what a chip
architect lives for is a new workload
right in static state at equilibrium
nobody changes share in the chip world.
It's when new new workloads arise that
huge share changes, right? When a new
workload called Ethernet switching arose
in the late 90s, all the incumbents
died. Every one of them, Nortell
Networks, Threecom, you go through this
list of of companies, all dead. When a
new workload arose in the mid the mid
2000s, right? all the existing players,
AMD, Intel, they had fabs, they had all
the architects, they got zero share of
of compute for phones. And so when we
looked out, what we saw was, holy cow,
there's a new workload coming.
And we believed we could build a a
company that that would would would
accelerate this workload. And we
believed there would be enough of this
workload to make it worthwhile building
a company.
And uh in every one of our forecasts for
the first time in my career, we were
wrong on
we we estimated it was it was smaller
than it was going to be. It's my fifth
startup. Every single estimate we've
ever had before this company, we guessed
on that two the market was going to be
bigger than we than uh than it actually
was. In this case, we we guessed the
market was going to be smaller than it
is. And what's happened over the last 18
months is this explosion.
Remember, we make AI with with training,
but we use it with inference.
And as AI has gotten smart enough to be
useful, what we're watching is a a sea
change, a wave of it being used. And
when it's used, speed matters.
And our our premise 10 years ago,
probably seven years too early was that
that speed would matter, that we could
build a machine that was 10, 20, 30, 50
times faster than a GPU.
And so that's a very long way of saying
what's the last 18 months been like? We
have a 25 billion backlog,
right? We are uh we will increase
manufacturing by 8x this year and 8x
next year.
Um we entered the year with several
hundred megawws under under management
and we'll we'll we'll end this year with
contracts for gigawatts.
Um, it is a just an extraordinary time
and I I I tell people that the the the
right way to to to get the timing right
in the startup is to be wrong for a long
time and not be dead.
And and that's what happened to us. I
mean, we we we invented this. We solved
this problem. Maybe this is longer than
than the answer.
>> No, no.
>> Um,
>> it's good drum. We we we solved a
problem that everybody in the industry
said couldn't be solved. Uh that with
the exception maybe of AI and Andy
Bethshy and maybe Lipu, everybody said
you're out of your mind. Um and in 2020
we we solved it. We delivered it to
market and absolutely nobody cared.
We had solved a 75year-old problem in
the computer industry. We had achieved
what was one of the holy grails and
absolutely nobody cared because fast AI
didn't make any sense when the AI was
dumb
and now the AI is smart and getting
faster getting smarter at an
extraordinary rate and everybody wants
answers more quickly.
And the final thing is uh uh it's not
easy being married it turns out in a in
a great market.
Um, my wife says that that, you know,
when nobody wanted to buy my stuff, I
was stressed at 11. And now everybody
wants to buy our stuff and I'm stressed
at 11.
And I told her that in 33 years of
marriage, maybe you should learn
something about my stress level.
Um, but that's what it's like. It is an
extraordinary time.
I think for those of you who who are
from the valley, uh right now the the
level of intensity and the excitement
around AI in the valley is is unlike
anything we've ever seen.
Yesterday, my first meeting was 7 a.m.
at a coffee shop in Menllo Park, and
there were about 20 other people doing
AI meetings at 7 a.m. on a Sunday. And
that that's that's what's going on right
now. And it's it's really a pleasure to
be a part of.
The models keep getting smarter. Is the
hardware keeping up or are we running
today's AI on yesterday's machine? Atik
and Dave.
>> Well, we're definitely running on on
yesterday's GPUs that were designed for
graphics and video games. And you know,
it's funny. They when you talk to the
people who are now, you know,
multi-billionaires, decillionaires,
none of them saw it coming. They were
busy building the best conceivable GPUs
for video games. And it was the AI
researchers in the basements that said,
"Hey, our algorithms will run better on
that chip." And I think the audience for
that was pretty limited at that point in
time. They're like, "Yeah, we don't care
about you." Boy, did that invert in a
hurry. But, you know, one of the
byproducts of the way technology
evolved, you know, I think Andrew, you
said your your IPO was biggest
semiconductor IPO of all time, but I
think it was actually the first or
second biggest IPO of all time, period.
>> It was the biggest before SpaceX came
up. before. Yeah. And it was funny
because it's the the top of the pyramid,
you know, being the coolest kid in town
has a very short shelf life these days.
[laughter]
But you at least you had it. You had
>> the Chrysler building.
>> That's a good lesson. [laughter]
>> But you know, it's funny. I was talking
to Andrew about two things. First of
all, the humility uh with that level of
success having the biggest IPO of all
time. The humility in the moment is just
mindboggling to me. It's just so cool.
But the other thing he said was if you
look for people who are aware of AI
algorithms and transistors at the same
time in their head they just there
there's like one in a million engineers
spans that top to bottom. And why did
this happen? It happened because you
know the biggest IPO before that was
Meta. Meta is social media. Before that
was Google. And it's all software
software Python Python. You know no
one's thinking about chips. No one's
thinking about fab. the entire fab
industry moved to Asia. We just
completely lost the core and all of a
sudden like it has flipped and now all
[laughter] of a sudden but we just don't
have the people who can think from hey
this transformer change will require
this transistor to operate or load in
this way and boy if you if you develop
that skill set you are in huge demand at
cerebrus and everywhere.
Well, basically
that is true today because uh you know
AI came on so fast. But the entire
history of process technologies and
semiconductors
has been on the basis of analyzing the
workload and trying to build machines
that will execute the workload all the
way back to even Alan Turing. I mean we
stand on his shoulders. I mean my entire
career, my life, association even with
Andrew all comes from that person
starting and thinking about how to build
a machine that would execute the problem
that he was facing
to go from there to processes in the
early days. In a way I see analoges even
at that time that the problem always
remained on exactly how the processing
has to be done very fast on the workload
that is available and how you feed the
processor from memory. How do you enable
that continuum of not having a
bottleneck either at the memory stage or
at the processing stage that came
through multiple generations and you
know when I was being introduced you
talked about being there early yes I
have seen shockly sitting in his office
yes I've competed with the you know the
entire Gordon Moore you know the guy who
has a law associated with his name I've
competed and beaten his company when
they were a juggernaut that was so
powerful none of you may be old enough
to remember when Intel was so powerful
that even Microsoft would not cross the
line with them. That was the time with a
handful of people. We started off
addressing the same problem. We
introduced techniques of working on the
workload that was available at that time
and we introduced things like uh uh out
of order execution
um uh branch prediction of prefetching
and then later on we went on to see that
there was again a bottleneck being
created as you had to get more memory
fetches and uh then hardware assistance
in scheduling of instructions.
all that happened and uh that brings us
to to this time when suddenly the
workload has started transforming at an
extremely rapid pace. So I don't take
everything away from Jensen that he
basically was uh building graphics
chips. I remember I was on the advisory
council of Stanford School of
Engineering and Jensen already had
become famous because of his graphic
shifts and I met him and I said JJSen
what are you thinking about right now
and he said I'm trying to get GPUs into
data centers to be part of the compute
workload execution
and I said but your GPUs are unusable
I've been trying to get my company to
use them at that time there was software
company I was
But they are so hard to use and that's
when he said I will address that
problem. I will and he developed CUDA
the ability to distribute uh the
workload onto his GPUs. He gave uh he
gave uh his machines to Stanford for
them to use in the uh mathematical
engineering um uh labs that they had
over there.
Fast forward to what Andrew was talking
about.
Now I have long association with Andrew
because if you work in this field you
know each other you know who's doing
what and this is with cerebras when I
first basically was described cerebras
and you know some of his key people have
worked for me and when he when he
described it to me at that time AI was
not on the horizon. It was high
performance computing that this was
built for. But the problem that he was
solving was the right one. The problem
he was solving was taking care of the
basically the flow of of uh the workload
from memory
from processor to processor
into the ability to then processes. So
he was creating a platform which had
architectural innovation and physical
innovation where the memory was very
close to the processor and the other
processors were also very close to the
process. What he showed as a single chip
basically is translating an architecture
onto a platform.
As we go forward,
the problem is going to get worse and
worse and there will be a time then he
will have to do something more than what
he is doing. But every new innovation
that is coming is dealing with the
problem of a bottleneck occurring now
with AI particularly as the AI workload
itself is transforming. It used to be
training then it moves to
consumerdominated inference. Now it is
going to enterprise inference and then
within enterprise inference the
transformation is occurring again and
the way it is occurring is that AI in
the meantime has opened up the context
window. Opening up the context window is
basically an invitation for unstructured
huge amount of everything to be sucked
into it. When that happens, your
inference is not a single stage
inference like you have with a consumer
or an initial enterprise environment. It
is a multi-stage inference and it has
fanouts and now it is carrying forward
any ambiguity in in in the assignment of
weights in the tokens is going to also
backfire on you even the slightest
change. So now what happens is that with
this enormous transformation in the
workload every step has to retain the
reference to the context of the answer
of that step as is going to be used by
the next step.
This is going to be incredibly memory
intensive. We haven't seen the end of it
and uh we will have to have new
innovations that address this
even a step but in the same direction as
what Cerebras was trying to do. And if
you take a look at some of the new
companies that are coming on the
horizon, they're including things like
in-memory compute.
Inmemory compute was originally only a
dream to be used at the very very edge.
Now they're talking about using it for
data centers, but the idea is the same.
How do you basically enable the
interaction between memory and compute
to be as low a latency as possible, as
efficiently translatable as possible. It
can't be done alone by hardware. It will
need scheduling also of the workload
itself.
>> All right. Thank you. Uh, um, I have a
bunch of questions for you, Andrew. We
want you to answer them real quick and
then uh Atique and Dave if you could
weigh in is he right is he wrong or do
you know something that Andrew doesn't
know okay so what is the real bottleneck
if you could remove only one constraint
on AI tomorrow compute memory networking
or electricity which one would you
remove and will your answer be the same
three years from now I
>> I think right now all of us are
constrained by data center availability
the entire industry I think we're trying
to move at this enormous a speed sort of
the speed of software and data centers
move like real estate
and that's holding us all back
>> right three years from now are you are
you evading that question
>> I'm not evading uh I'm ducking and
covering um
uh I I think in in three years it will
be uh fab capacity
>> yeah okay I'm going to go to a hundred
billion dollar question but before I do
is he right? Is he wrong? Or do you know
something he doesn't know that could be
helpful?
>> I think knows a lot. I don't know.
>> Right. He's absolutely right. But the
main thing is there are things that we
can fix
people sitting on this table or we can
influence or be involved in fixing and
those that we can't.
>> Okay.
>> Energy and building data centers
physically we can't fix. That has to be
fixed elsewhere. What goes inside those
data centers that we can influence and
fix. Yeah. Okay, watch this. Dave's
going to say something profound and
shocking.
>> Well,
what we do right now at AI Inference is
utterly idiotic. That the weights do not
need to move. And yet, we use massive
amounts of energy in HPM, the most
expensive chips in the world to move the
weights out of HPM memory into a GPU,
use them for a picoscond, and then dump
them. It's utterly idiotic. I know
Andrew knows this because we've met and
talked at his office about it. Uh there
are solutions that are a thousand to a
millionx more efficient. The only reason
those don't exist already is because the
supply chain doesn't move quickly enough
and the software people are are
innovating at such an incredible rate
that nobody wants to hardwire something
and find out it was wrong. But when we
get the supply chain figured out, which
will be easily within three years, we'll
be running uh most likely on the upper
end of a thousand to millionx more
efficiently by not moving the weights.
>> All right, I have a lot of questions.
Next question. the hundred billion
dollar question. We're committing
hundreds of billions of dollars to AI
infrastructure. Are we building the
foundation of the next economy? Are we
overbuilding the biggest technology
bubble in history? Uh what is this
pets.com or whatever? What would that's
a 2000 reference um for those
millennials or Gen Z. What would have to
be true for all this capacity to earn an
economic return?
>> You know, no, he's I'm going to him. You
get to say if he's right or wrong.
I just want to make a comment. You know,
I am old enough to remember there was a
company called Digital Equipment.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Deck.
>> Deck. It was
>> General Durio put 70,000 into it. It was
headto-head with IBM.
>> I know.
>> It's not anymore.
>> Why?
Because the answer that Ken Olsson gave
is I cannot imagine so many people
requiring little computers.
>> Yeah. Ken Olsson worked on Project
Whirlwind, which was at MIT that spun
out Silicon Valley. You don't get
Silicon Valley without Project
Whirlwind. And his co-founder is an MIT
guy, by the way. All right. So, what's
the answer to that$und00 billion dollar
question?
>> I I don't think there's any doubt we're
building the foundation for for a
fundamentally different economy. I I I
think there will be bumps along the way.
I I think if you take a 10 or 15year
view of Pets.com, it it turns out that
that pet food online is really good
business.
>> Chewy.
>> Chewy. And a huge portion of of what
Amazon does and a large portion of the
total pet food business is now sold
online. I I think there will be bumps
along the way, right? There will be bad
ideas that we adopt for a little bit.
There'll be sort of culde-sacs in
innovation culde-sacs that we'll have to
back out of and keep going. But I I I
think the following and I I said this at
at a te's house. I I I think if uh I
think there's a chance that someone born
in 20 years
never knows anyone who dies of cancer
and never knows anybody who's hit by a
drunk driver.
Okay? And the number one killer of of
healthy adults is is car accidents. Um
the number of uh the number one killer
of of everybody is cancer. And so I I I
think we will solve big and interesting
problems
um in in the next 20 25 years and that
that will change what it is to grow up
and to to live in our society.
>> So my next set of questions about uh AI
when it's 10 times faster. But Dave, did
you want to weigh in right, wrong, or
you know something that he doesn't?
Well, so it drives me nuts when people
compare what's going on right now to
pets.com because the internet, you know,
I I was really fortunate to graduate
college right when the internet was
exploding and taking off and it worked
out incredibly lucky for me. But um
everyone's like, "Yeah, but then it
overheated and collapsed." Yeah. But
then Google was born right in the middle
of the collapse and Google just and look
how look where Google is now. Uh look
where we are now. Yeah. I mean I it's
like was the internet a bubble? No. The
internet is the foundation of basically
everything we do now. It was never a
bubble. Uh, it's just people panicked
and bailed out and gave up on it. That
always happens in America. It will
inevitably happen in Wings of AI. AI
will still 20 years from today be the
biggest thing that's happened in human
history by far. I mean, Andrew's
characterization is exactly right. And
so, yeah, America always overheats.
Yeah, the capital always floods into the
wrong little nooks and crannies and it
collapses and people say, "See, I was
right all along." No, AI is here to
stay. It's going to be massive.
>> All right. Speed versus intelligence.
Have we spent too much time asking how
intelligent a model is and not enough
time asking how fast it can think as
someone who is is like at the forefront
of speed?
>> So, I'm uh
now that I'm a public market CEO, what I
see around me is everybody selling their
own book all the time.
Everybody telling me what what I should
do because it's in their interest.
Um I as somebody who builds fast
hardware I I we're not delusional that
that dumb fast is not helpful to anybody
right but what's happened is the the
models have gotten so smart
and are on a trajectory to continue that
that speed has jumped to the four. The
open source models are really smart the
closed source models are really smart.
The small models are really smart. And
in that environment, what you want is an
answer quickly, right? Um, you know what
I what I like to say is if your
12-year-old has been naughty, don't take
away their phone. Set it to dialup rate,
right? That's a punishment,
right? The getting the inability to get
to to to where you want to go quickly is
a punishment. And that that shows you
how important speed is. And so that
that's that's my answer.
>> Great. All right.
>> I think I think it's one of the most
important questions of this next coming
year because you know we're seeing with
these smaller Chinese models like GLM
equal or very close to equal frontier
benchmarks, but the parameter count is
down significantly a factor of four or
more. uh if you can get the parameter
count down on a model and have it be
just as good at a task and then you can
fit it all onto a single cerebrus or a
set of 10 cerebrous wapers, you pick up
a factor of 10 to 100 in throughput.
So the question is if that works, you
you got to keep in mind that what we use
right now for AI surprised everybody and
it was trained on every word ever
written by humanity, including every
Reddit post, every Trump tweet, every,
you know, Taylor Swift concert. It's all
in there. And when you ask it a
question, it's like, yeah, I know all
about Taylor Swift's, you know, eraser.
Like, well, I don't need that knowledge
to do this task where I'm trying to
write code. I'm trying to design a chip.
I'm trying to design a rocket ship. If I
can get the parameter count down yet be
just as smart within a domain, then it
all fits in much smaller memory and it's
blazing fast. So, possibility of that is
incredible. Sorry, I
>> I want to address what Dave said because
this is an extremely important area as
AI transitions from just data centers to
the edge and to edge devices like
robotics and even to basically handheld
devices which can operate without making
cloud calls because here the scale that
you provide has to be much less. The
accuracy may have to be more.
the weight ambiguity may have to go down
significantly for it to match the
underlying hardware's ability to
execute.
>> So all right, my next question is um
you've said speed is productivity. Give
us an examp
150,000 people who are dying may not die
because of that. But let's get specific.
give us an example of what becomes
possible at 10x uh today's inference
speed and what simply isn't possible now
um you know maybe you're too busy on the
speed and not thinking about this but
but people must be saying oh with what
you've created I could do this imagine
the same intelligence
>> but responses are 10 times faster and 10
times cheaper what new applications
suddenly become possible I mean this is
when we have a symbiotic relationship
with technology that you know we just
haven't thought of black and white to
bring us into color.
>> Okay.
So, let let's think about what speed
does across the the landscape of
technology, right? Netflix began doing
what? Shipping DVDs via mail in
envelopes.
>> CDROM. Yep.
>> Right. And then the internet got fast
and they didn't become better at
shipping DVDs and envelopes. They became
a movie studio,
right? They were able to bypass
traditional theaters
and for very little money they were able
to get right into millions and millions
of homes and they became something
fundamentally different. And if you had
to wait four hours for your movie to
download, that would never happen.
That time and time again in our
industry, speed has unlocked
new ideas and new markets.
Right? Coding agents aren't interesting
if they're slow. They're also not
interesting if they're dumb, but once
they're good enough, they're not
interesting if they're slow. Personal
agents, some of the fastest growing
applications right now are uh Instinct
and Muse and this collection of
personalized agents.
If you have to wait eight minutes for it
to order a burrito for you, right? One,
you could almost drive there and get it.
or two, you can go to the computer, your
phone, and you can order it yourself,
right? The the ability to execute and do
things with AI is fundamental. And if
you think of something like the guys at
who are doing law or accounting, right,
their whole business model is to bill
every six minutes, right? Maybe it would
be less offensive if they got 30 times
as much done in that six minutes,
right? Um and and so when when we look
out into the landscape,
>> calling lawyers offensive,
>> uh I I think it's it's an Yeah. Um I I
think a billing model of every time you
call me is offensive or I call you Yeah,
I think that's not good. Um
>> fe suckers.
>> Well, there some Yeah, sometimes they're
really really valuable, but not in six
minute blocks. Um, I I I think that that
the making of the stuff we do and even
if you look out into your your daily
life at work, you know how much time is
spent in a in an enterprise taking
things out of workday and organizing it
so it can go into ADP,
right? just stupid like
manipulation of stuff from one to
another or going from one from
Salesforce to your accounting tools. All
the all this goes away and quickly and
it changes what what our organizations
can be and what they are and how we're
going to be organized and all all of
those are are only made possible if you
don't have to wait forever to get it
done.
>> What do you guys think? um you know he's
in the eye of the storm you know
building this but you know you guys are
futurists and following trends
>> I I think speed is directly translated
into less human effort to get a far
better result it just and and a really
simple example of that is the vision
transformer like if you wrote code six
months ago and you're trying to put a
guey on it so you know what the hell is
going on it just flat out gave you
garbage and the solution turned out to
show the model what it built visually
and have it learn to understand what you
like. And this the solution there is
called a vision transformer. You just
take an image and you cut it into 16 by6
pixel little chunks and you pretend each
chunk is a word and you throw it right
back into the same LLM that read every
Trump tweet and you say, "Pretend this
is language and just freaking tell me
what's going on in this image." Nobody
thought that would work, but with enough
speed, it just flat out works. So now,
if you're building an interface on top
of whatever you're building, it actually
looks at its own interface and says,
"Yeah, I built garbage. Let me work on
it again." Okay, now this is something
you're going to like. And then when
you're talking to the AI, you're like,
"Those buttons are messed up." You
literally prompt it messed up. And it
says, "You're right. I'll fix them."
Could not do that six months ago. That
unlock is pure speed.
But there are consequences and I'm not a
fear-monger
but when basically
these capabilities are enabling Navia
Stokes equations to be solved where
Terrence Tao field medalist basically is
worried about what he's going to be
doing if these tools are going to be
solving problems.
It is not unfounded that we should take
a pause and think about the
socioeconomic impact that this is going
to have.
So if we were designing the AI computer
from scratch today and I don't maybe
this is futile because you know there's
so much we're building on not inheriting
decades of computer architecture
would it look anything like what we're
building now and if we were doing that
what disappears first
I mean if if you're building it from
scratch for the future all of the matt
moles would be photonic for sure uh and
then all of the processing between the
madm moles would be normal transistor
math and
>> well basically there are three things
you know there is connectivity memory
and processing
and he's right about the connectivity
the connectivity has to go into a
photonic regime the question is does
compute and memory go into photonic
regime we haven't wrapped our brain
around that possibility yet completely I
>> I think it's really important you you
hear what just said and sort Think about
it. All of computer architecture is one
of three things. We try and make the
calculations faster or more efficient.
We have to store results and move them
to calculations. And then we've got to
move the results to some place where
they're useful. That's IO, right? That's
your core, your memory, and your IO. And
everything we do is on one of those
three dimensions. And he just snuck that
in as if it were obvious. But you can
simplify all of computer architecture
into those three things. Right? Our
innovations were about how we moved
compute, how we move data from memory to
compute. We were able to use a different
type of memory. We're able to put it
much closer and thereby widen the
aperture so we could move data more
quickly.
All right. What Dave's talking about is
well, what if we do the calculations
more quickly? What if we keep them in
the optical domain? That would be super
cool. you got to store the results
somewhere. We don't quite know how to do
that yet. We do know how to move results
and we know that if you move results in
the optical domain, they move very
quickly and for very little power. And
so what you're going to see and each
time you you you read about a a chip
company or a new architecture, you ask
yourself on which domain, which of these
three dimensions have they delivered
innovation? the cores are faster and
more efficient, right? Have they done
some sort of innovation on memory or
memory bandwidth? Or is this an IO
innovation? Are they moving data off
chip to where it's going to be used more
quickly, more efficiently for less
power? And with that very simple
framework, you understand all of comput
architecture. That's all we do. Turns
out it's really hard, but I I do want
you to note that the te just snuck that
in like it was obvious.
What is AI architecture of the future
look like?
>> I I I think what we know for at least
the the next several years is it will be
transformer-based,
right? I I think that's number one. Um I
I think that uh while there are many
people who who who can point to the
flaws of trans of transformers, we we do
now have a dominant design and we have
uh the the leading five or six companies
that are pouring huge resources into
improving transformer-based
architectures. If you unpack a
transformer, transformer particularly
attention head is a big matrix multiply.
Right? So that that's what we've got to
understand and get better at. Um I I
think there are lots of different ideas
of how you might do that. Those will all
play out. And the proof isn't in in sort
of in marketing. The proof isn't in
presentations at conferences. It's can
you build it and can you build enough of
it that it it can be deployed
>> and that's what we're going to see.
>> Who are want to point out that you have
Daniela Roose over here on the
>> Yeah. She has gone in a different
direction Andrew
basically taking a look at attention at
a fundamental level and trying to change
the granularity of that attention and it
has produced results that show the
ability to execute inference
three four times faster.
>> We'll take it. I
>> so I I I don't want to you know
basically completely
overlook the possibility that there are
ways to address the attention issue
without transformers or with something
with finer granularity mathematically.
>> I that would be a huge win for the whole
community.
>> That's liquid AI.
>> Yeah, liquid AI.
>> That's liquid.
>> I think there's been you know with the
recent Chinese models a big
reconciliation between the two paths.
So, so you know when we embargoed the
chips to from China, they started
innovating like crazy on quantization
straight transformers quantize reduce
the data types as much as possible and
it's worked shockingly well which
completely changes the speed and
throughput the memory everything uh but
also the matmals you know because when
when the when the transformers were
being invented all the researchers are
working in PyTorch on CUDA and they're
all using FP32 numbers because you don't
even think In Python, you don't think
about data types. It just deals with it.
So everything's running in FP32.
>> Now it's becoming really obvious that
you can shrink the the weights and the
activations to much much smaller data
types. I haven't heard anyone trying to
optimize data types since I was at MIT,
you know, in in the 1990s. Nobody cared
after everything moved up to high level
languages. Now suddenly everybody cares
a lot. So the Chinese innovate like
crazy on quantization changes
everything. And that's straight
transformers. Meanwhile,
>> we starved them of compute and so lo and
behold, they found more efficient ways
to do compute.
>> Exactly. Right. We starved them of
Nvidia chips and they innovated like
crazy.
>> Yes. I was I was in China giving a
keynote and after in the in the session
in between uh the keynote and the next
speech, one of the guys came over and he
said, "Tik
I did my PhD at Stanford. Let me just
tell you now I'm a venture capitalist.
The best thing that has happened to me
is that you have shut off uh our
availability of uh GPUs coming to China.
Now I can start investing. Until now,
you know, everything was coming from
America. There was no innovation
possible. Now we can innovate because
you're going to starve us.
>> That that's not a partisan statement, by
the way. That embargo started in the
Biden administration and was accelerated
in the Trump administration. There's no
party component to this. It's just the
entire strategy has forced insane
amounts of innovation in China and now
we're scrambling to actually backport
it. You know, meanwhile in the US, a lot
of the research was in states based
models, liquid AI being a great example
and and that uses FP32 high resolution
numbers. But now, uh, with the new Kimmy
models, the K3, you know, it goes normal
attention layer, then three KDA layers,
which are state spaces, then a normal
attention layer, and then three more
KDAs, which are a state space. I think
that is it very much feels like a normal
transformer but it reconciles
>> architecture different.
>> So so in five years who do you bet on US
or Chinese AI architecture and uh add in
robots to that after you tell us who's
winning in five years.
>> Well it it's not not great to say but
we're getting clobbered in robots. I
mean, I I think anybody who who sees
industrial robots as as an interesting
domain, if you go to China, where
they're so far ahead, it's embarrassing.
And it's also embarrassing how far ahead
they are in the supply chain. I I to the
best of my knowledge, there are zero
zero credible US actuator makers, right?
And that that's the the most important
part of a robot, the most important
mechanical part of a robot. And so we we
are certainly not ahead on robots.
>> So what about just in general in terms
of AI architecture five years?
>> I I I think right now what's happened is
the uh over multiple generations
the closed source models have gotten
much better and the gap between them has
stayed remarkably similar. call it six
months, four months, eight months,
somewhere in there that as the the the
frontier has moved, so too has the open
source edge.
And I I I don't see any particular
reason why that changes that that Kimmy
is
four, six, eight months behind
uh behind the best of Open AI and
Anthropic. And I don't see why that that
changes
uh in in the next several years.
>> The main thing is that if you're behind
even by a small amount, the inefficiency
that is created actually works against
you multiplied many times over when
you're working in the new agentic
environment.
>> This is
>> so you end up basically even if the if
the models are free spending more on the
compute.
>> It's like Yoda wisdom. Exactly.
[laughter]
>> There are two things, right? And and it
it has varied by industry.
Um Dell for many years said they were a
fast follower
and they spent a remarkably little bit
of their massive revenue on R&D, an
absurdly small amount. Um
if you are not on the frontier,
uh the frontier can't help you with your
next model.
And so we did a big deal with OpenAI. We
delivered to them the fastest inference
compute in the world. And you know what
they did with it for the first six
months? They gave it all to their
engineers.
>> All of it. Because it was more helpful
to them in accelerating their their own
development than it was worth it to them
to get revenue from it from from
customers. So the first thing is is on
the frontier you are uh you can use your
next generation to help build your
current generation. The other side of
the equation is is uh if you're a uh an
innovation taker, you can distill
and that's much much less costly, right?
You can learn from what they did. And
the battle here is exactly there. The
Chinese models are heavily dependent on
the frontier models for some of their
insights and for creating data for their
innovations.
And so you have two competing forces.
And right now over the last two years
they've sort of played to a draw and
that's a a gap of n months. Ada Love
Lace, Einstein, Tesla. Who are the
future,
you know, Einstein's in the space that
we should watch tonight? You're going to
go to the AI 100 gala, I assume.
>> Yeah.
>> Yep. How much business are you going to
get done there by talking to the other
people that are anointed as, you know,
the people doing the stuff? Are you just
going to, you know, you're not the
biggest extrovert. Are you going to get
things done
>> at that meeting? What do you want to
accomplish? And then and then who are
the people all three of you are tracking
right now? Because we need innovators.
We can't just become couch potatoes like
in Wall-E. Uh we need to figure out what
to do right now. Uh and if not you, who?
Well, I I think one of the really
exciting parts about uh this market is
that the most knowledgeable people are
just finishing their PhDs,
right? A and that in the AI category,
right, it's an upside down labor market.
Coming out of MIT, coming out of
Stanford with a PhD, you are at the
absolute leading edge. And if you've
been in industry and you have to sit in
some meetings every day, and you've got
a you're in your mid-30s, which used to
be the the peak of a technical career,
mid-30s, mid-4s, right? The domain
experts are actually much much younger
than you. And that's super interesting.
>> They're going to reverse mentor. That's
right. That's right.
>> Not gonna do some internship with some
young Turk. The young Turk is going to
make sure you become relevant and not
irrelevant.
>> That's sort of fun, right? That that's
really exciting that that what's
happening is we have a a wellspring of
insight and of innovation. This is at
the AI level. Now, at the chip layer
where we build stuff, uh there are
tremendous returns to experience.
It's hard. It takes a long time to learn
how to build a chip, to do the logic, to
do the the backend, the place and route,
have a relationship with the fab um the
IP vendors. And so you you've got this
collection of new providing enormous
value and experience providing enormous
value in a way that that we haven't seen
before.
>> 100% right. I was going to say exactly
that that on the semiconductor side on
the chip side on the building side even
the application of modern physics optics
etc that experience the cumulative
experience is a very very important
ingredient right whereas on the other
side he's absolutely right you know the
young kids who are coming out of school
they know so much we are running as fast
as possible just to keep up with the
latest knowledge
Dave, you're thinking a lot about
talent. What what's your take on this?
>> Yeah, well, the the people graduating
right now are the very first to be truly
AI native. Uh, and there's no going back
once you've taken the red pill. Uh, but
if you think about Einstein as an
analogy, you know, Einstein was
completely unrecognized,
sitting in the patent office, coming up
with the most brilliant ideas in the
history of humanity, and everyone's
like, I don't believe it. And so it's,
you know, years and years and years
later that people will get discovered
and recognized that's not going to be
true of this next generation. They're
working with hundreds, thousands and
soon tens of thousands of AI agents
every day. And if their ideas are right,
if they solve Navier Stokes and it's
right, it's just right. And so I I think
that this next generation coming out of
MIT, Harvard, Princeton, Northeastern,
they're like nobody I've ever seen.
Their their productivity, their
confidence, their energy is like nothing
I've ever seen. And I think there's a
tipping point in there where the AI
natives, you know, they they they kind
of started with GPT3 or two and they've
grown with it and they're not going
back. And so those are predominantly
very very young, super optimistic,
hyperenergetic people. So
>> Stanford are also not bad. I just want
to put in a plug for them.
>> Oh, did I miss that one? Yeah. So I want
to ask uh about what's the new Moore's
law, Andrew? But before I do,
>> um, as we move the frontier forward,
what will be going away as hardware?
People talked about, you know, uh,
everything disappears, ubiquit, you
know, when the internet creates
ubiquity, and I don't know if we really
got that, but I do think we're entering
an era where where things do disappear.
I I don't know what disappears. I I I
think um
certainly
in a data center the uh the things we
use
many of them had have not had pressure
on them for decades. For example,
there's a shortage right now of of
generators of gas generators because we
use them for backup in data centers. Um,
these generators are have had no
innovation in 30 years. They're
horrible. I mean, Caterpillar, Giver
Nova, all these guys. And suddenly,
right, we had there's so much pressure
on them. We've got innovation happening
in in in diesel gen sets, in turbines,
and uh in fuel cells, um, in power
switching. All these things were tired,
quiet little industries in a corner. And
we've got huge innovation there because
they're part of the data center supply
chain. Um on the compute side, we right
now we need more of everything, right?
There's not enough memory, there not
enough CPUs, there not enough GPUs,
there not enough accelerators, um there
not enough printed circuit boards, there
there not enough substrates, there not
enough power regulators. there just you
go through the list and um the whole
supply chain is is stretched past
breaking.
>> All right. Tokens, legacy, uh memory,
bandwidth. What's the new Moore's law
for AI?
>> I I certainly So Moors law said we could
drop down new transistors about 18 at
what double every 18 months. Double
every 18 months.
>> Tique was probably in the room came up
with it.
>> I was actually
[laughter]
Uh
um I grew up on the Stanford campus and
William Shockley was my neighbor, right?
And Shockley invented our neighbor to
him.
>> Yeah. He invented the transistor and the
only thing we knew growing up was that
his wife gave full-size candy bars at
Halloween,
right? [laughter] That's what it was
like growing up at at Stanford. He he
was not a nice human. Um his wife was
okay, though. Um I I think uh for a long
time we haven't been able to ring twice
as much compute out of those transistors
and then the gap moved from 18 months to
to three or four years. But I think
right now the models are certainly
getting more than 2x smarter every 18
months. And there'll be certainly some
sort of architectural graph you can
point to to the the rate at which these
models are uh are improving in
intelligence. And my guess is it's it's
not a line, it's an exponential.
>> You guys knew Mo's law. the Mors law
lasted a long long time because
transistors were shrinking and the type
of compute was this exploding range of
compute types you know everything from
simulation to video games it's huge
range um AI is different AI is a couple
of very very simple highly scalable
operations drive all thinking and so
what'll happen I think is you know a lot
of people visualize data centers all
over the world the whole earth is
covered by one big data center that's
never going to
First of all, we're going to make chips
as fast as we possibly can for the next
three or four years. Fabs take a long
time to build. So, we're constrained in
the number of chips. The physical
footprint of data centers is a tiny tiny
tiny fraction of the earth no matter
what because we can't make the chips any
faster uh until the new fabs come
online. But within four years, we'll
discover new ways to compute that are
doing these very very simple operations
at blazing fast speeds that will look
nothing like a normal GPU or CPU. And so
those will come online right right when
you know four years from now has come
those will have been invented by AI and
we'll find we'll find that compute is
everywhere is my guess and that you can
compute in crystals you can compute in
substances you can compute in liquids
all these different ways to these do
these really three or four simple simple
operations that drive all of AI what
we'll find are incredibly abundant and
then that will drive the next millennium
of compute largely probably in space
largely you know using a ton of solar
energy that isn't hitting the earth uh
and that's the long-term horizon but it
won't it won't look like an Nvidia rack
floating around in space so
>> law laid the foundation of its death the
moment it was defined
>> because it basically was going to come
to an end when you reach atomic
dimensions
>> in the granularity of what you can
produce on silicon
similarly the efficiency of tokens are
also going to have a death because you
can't keep increasing the efficiency of
tokens forever. That will slow down
also.
>> All right. We hear constantly that power
in AI is concentrated in a handful of
companies. Sitting here in Silicon
Valley, does it actually feel that way?
And what does it feel like to break into
the club? Um, Andrew, and will Cerebras
ultimately acquire Nvidia or will Nvidia
ultimately acquire Cerebrris? Are you an
aqua hire?
[laughter]
>> I I I would like to make that phone call
to Jansen. We're we're we're we're
looking to buy you. Uh
I I think in many things in life as you
get better, uh as you grow, as you
learn, your appreciation for for what
others have done to get bigger and
better grows, right? My my wife and I
study Argentine tango and um as we've
done this over 30 years, it feels like
uh our distance between us and pros has
gotten larger, not smaller because we
appreciate a vast array of things
they're doing to make it look so good. I
think we've achieved a size at at 50
billion, 60 billion gives me enormous
appreciation what Jensen has achieved at
at five trillion,
right?
And for me, as somebody who tries to
learn from CEOs, it it wasn't CUDA. It
wasn't the GPU. Between 2003 and 2013,
that company traded for cash as a public
company for a decade. They were nobody.
And to be a CEO and fight like that for
a decade as a public company until the
world until you got it right, I for me
is exciting. and and and I hold that up
as something we can learn from and and
be better at and and so that level of
grit. And so I I I I don't think that um
sort of you get to some size and and you
you rest on your laurels. You there
always people who are better. There
always companies that are bigger who you
can learn from. There always companies
that are smaller you can learn from.
>> So are you going to sit in the corner
tonight at the gala or are you going to
network your ass off?
Um, the good thing about about AI, you
my my mother's a a developmental
psychologist and and she came to one of
our our company meetings and and uh she
she said that that she was surprised
that that my social skills were at the
top and then she looked around and she
said, "Well, it took a room full of high
function autistics, Andrew, for your
social skills to be at the top." I think
we have the advantage uh in our
industry, for me anyway, of a lot of
guys don't like making eye contact and
and so as a result, I I do okay by
trying to wander around and bump into
people every now and again and and
hopefully make a new friend.
>> All right, my closing question. You are
one of four co-founders. I think three
is a new thousand. What should people be
building right now to all of you? What
should people be building? We we've
talked about the technical
breakthroughs. you know, you both have a
connection with Shockley, you know, uh,
through candy bars or being in the room.
Um, what should the next generation be
building as we have a symbiotic
relationship with AI? I mean, I think
the AIS are going to be talking to the
AIs and talking to the other AIs, but
what needs to be built and what what
what what role does human,
you know, creativity and intelligence
play uh, going forward?
>> So, I I have a thought for those of you
who are thinking of starting companies.
Um, build stuff you like to build.
Um, Aik and I have been building
hardware when hardware was cool and when
it wasn't cool, right? We were cool in
the mid to late 90s with the rise of
networking. And then starting in about
2001, 2002, we were uncool for 15 years,
16 years. There were very few hardware
companies started.
But I like building hardware. I like the
the the people. I I like the problem.
it's a good fit for my mind and whether
it's cool or whether other people wanted
it at the time. Uh what was was sort of
less important to me. This is what I
like doing and I like surrounding myself
by people who also like building
hardware and these are systems chips and
printed circuit boards and systems and
have a collection of problems. And so I
I think my advice is because the world
wants ducks. Don't stop being a leopard.
I mean, if you're a leopard, go do
leopard stuff, and your career will be
uh really enjoyable. If you find
problems that are a good fit for you,
that you're passionate about, and if you
keep doing it and you're really good at
it, over time, the market will swing in
and you'll be in favor. And there'll be
times when you're not in favor, but it
won't really matter because you'll be
doing stuff you really like to do.
So, you know, I'm older than Andrew
and uh you know, I I don't build things
right now myself.
I don't have the same energy as I as is
required, which is a lot to build
hardware. The energy required is
incredible. The amount of effort that
goes into detail planning is just
mind-boggling.
Andrew knows that very well. building
not just the compute engine but an
engineering marvel that he built at
Cibbras. It's just unbelievable.
>> Is he going to screw it up?
>> No, he's not going to screw it up. He
He's done it. He's done it along the
way, but his people, not him, but I know
those guys also, you know, but I also
saw that he they got corrected before
the public knew it. But nevertheless
now the innovation has to happen in all
dimensions because right from the outset
in my career I always looked at workload
also. So the evolution of workload which
comes down to the work that has to be
done on the AI side on the evolution of
how that has to be uh built so that it
is scheduled so that not only do we
depend upon good hardware with memory
and and and interconnect and compute all
integrated as tightly possible as
tightly as possible. We also have to
look at the workload being better
scheduled across that hardware.
>> Dave, you have the last word then we got
to get to our next next panel. Okay. Uh
in the very short term uh if I were
starting new companies which I am
actually uh if you look at the
transformer layer just below it and just
above it just just below it you have
performance optimizations like standard
kernel is a good company here on
university have and there's a bunch of
others that are worth two 35 10x in the
compute stack which are suddenly worth a
trillion dollars. And then just above
the transformer you have chain of
thought reasoning is a brand new thing
in the world. It's less than what a year
a year old. If you can loop the AI
productively uh in a chain of thought,
it's massively better. So, you got these
really tactical opportunities. But in
the longer term, look at like uh Laya AI
and look at the full cell simulator and
think about what Andrew was saying in
terms of AI curing cancer. It's going to
have the effective brain power of a
population of billions. It's going to
think at insanely fast rates, but you
don't want to constrain it with physical
tests because then it just can't move
ahead. So, any place you can simulate or
create a feedback loop of data is
incredibly fertile this coming year.
>> So, for time, let's stand up and and uh
wave to our audience. You guys, thank
you. Um
get a lock a hair of this one and let's
clone them when it's legal. Keep up the
great work, Andrew. And uh um please uh
buy these. How much are they? Million.
>> Buy the whole machine.
>> Buy or buy the whole machine, not just
those.